Richard P. Unsworth Papers, 1927 -
Smith College Archives
This collection is organized into five series: General Activities and Interests Professional Life Writings Audiovisual The collection is open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives except where noted in the finding aid. The personal and professional papers of Richard P. Unsworth (1927-present) were acquired from Richard Unsworth in 2014. Unsworth, Richard P.; Trocme, Andre, 1901-1971. World War, 1939-1945 -- Underground movements -- France -- Le Chambon-sur-Lignon. Sex -- Religious aspects -- Christianity. Smith College--Religious life; Smith College--Faculty. Photographs. Notebooks. Account books. Audiocassettes. Letters. Sermons.
- Richard P. Unsworth Papers, 1927 -, Series I: General; (1900 - 2014); Richard P. Unsworth; RG 42_unsworth; 2 boxes (.9 linear ft.); 1900 - 2010 1945 - 2000 20 document boxes, 3 media boxes (9.5 linear ft.) Smith College Archives Northampton, MA; Chaplain of the College and Professor of Religion. Contains biographical material, correspondence, photographs, speeches, and writings.
- Series II: Activities and Interests, (1945 - 2014)
- Series III: Professional Life, (1950 - 2014)
- Series IV: Writings, (1950 - 2012)
- Series V: Audiovisual Material, (1960 - 2010)
- SERIES I: General
  - Curriculum Vitae 1946 - 1998 (Box 1)
  - Education: Harvard restricted (Box 1)
  - Education: Mount Hermon 1940 - 1979 (Box 1)
  - Education: Princeton restricted (Box 1)
  - Education: Yale restricted (Box 1)
  - Genealogy undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: children/grandchildren 1960 - 2013 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: friends 1950 - 2013 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: parents/siblings 1930 - 2000 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Joy Merritt Unsworth 1970 - 2000 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Richard Preston Unsworth 1950 - 2000 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Joy and Richard Unsworth 1950 - 2008 (Box 1)
  - Travel: Asia 1970 (Box 2)
  - Travel:Bonhoeffer/Westminster Abbey 1990 (Box 2)
  - Travel:Europe 1970 - 2008 (Box 2)
  - Travel:itineraries 1982 - 1986 (Box 2)
  - Travel:itineraries 1986 - 1987 (Box 2)
  - Travel:itineraries 1988 - 1989 (Box 2)
  - Travel:itineraries 1990 - 1991 (Box 2)
  - Travel:postcards 1975 - 2008 (Box 2)
  - Photographs 1900 - 2000 (Box 2)
  - Appointment Books 1970 - 1998 (Box 3)
- SERIES II: Activities and Interests
  - Civil Rights 1960 - 1990 (Box 4)
  - Education 1950 - 2000 (Box 4)
  - General 1950 - 2000 (Box 4)
  - Music 1960 - 2000 (Box 4)
  - Race 1960 - 2000 (Box 4)
  - Sex 1954 - 1985 (Box 4)
  - Yad Va Shem 1985 - 2000 (Box 4)
- SERIES III: Professional Life
  - American School of Tangier 1988 (Box 5)
  - Asia Society: general 1999 - 2000 (Box 5)
  - Asia Society:"Indonesia Study" 1999 - 2000 (Box 5)
  - Asia Society:"National Commission on Asia in the Schools" 2000 - 2002 (Box 5)
  - Berkshire School: administrative restricted (Box 5)
  - Berkshire School: correspondence 1994 - 1996 (Box 5)
  - Brown University - "The American University and the Pluralist Ideal" 1985 - 1987 (Box 5)
  - College Cevenol 1960 - 2000 (Box 6)
  - Connecticut College - "Review of the Chaplaincy at Connecticut College" 1986 (Box 6)
  - Crossroads Africa 1960 - 1966 (Box 6)
  - Dartmouth College 1965 - 1968 (Box 6)
  - Eaglebrook School: board of trustees restricted (Box 6)
  - Eaglebrook School: correspondence 1998 (Box 6)
  - Five Colleges - alumni 1970 - 1979 (Box 6)
  - Harvard University - library committee 1995 - 2010 (Box 6)
  - Khan Institute: "Anatomy of an Exile" 2000 - 2001 (Box 7)
  - Khan Institute:"Ecologies of Children" 1997 - 1998 (Box 7)
  - Khan Institute:general 1996 - 2003 (Box 7)
  - Khan Institute:"How American Children Lead Their Lives" 2001 - 2002 (Box 7)
  - Khan Institute:"Religion and Value Information in a Diverse Society" 1997 - 2000 (Box 7)
  - Landmark Volunteers 1993 - 1994 (Box 7)
  - Mount Holyoke College 1993 - 1998 (Box 7)
  - Mount Washington School 1953 - 1959 (Box 7)
  - Northfield Mount Hermon: administrative restricted (Box 7)
  - Northfield Mount Hermon:correspondence 1980 - 1995 (Box 7)
  - Northfield Mount Hermon:Ford Cottage 1980 - 1995 (Box 7)
  - Northfield Mount Hermon:newsclippings 1980 - 1995 (Box 7)
  - Smith College: administrative restricted (Box 8)
  - Smith College:"Afro-American Committee" 1985 - 1990 (Box 8)
  - Smith College:committees 1954 - 1979 (Box 8)
  - Smith College:correspondence 1970 - 1989 (Box 8)
  - Smith College:courses 1953 - 1979 (Box 8)
  - Smith College:courses 1996 - 1998 (Box 8)
  - Smith College:Otelia Cromwell Day 1998 - 2004 (Box 8)
  - Smith College:retirement and resignation undated (Box 8)
  - Williams School 1998 (Box 8)
  - Yale University 1949 - 1953 (Box 8)
  - Conway funeral 1995 (Box 9)
  - services 1950 - 1959 (Box 9)
  - services 1960 - 1969 (Box 9)
  - services 1970 - 1979 (Box 9)
  - services 1980 - 2010 (Box 9)
  - Mendenhall funeral 1988 (Box 9)
  - baptisms, funerals, and weddings 1950 - 1959 (Box 10)
  - baptisms, funerals, and weddings 1960 - 1969 (Box 10)
  - baptisms, funerals, and weddings 1970 - 1979 (Box 10)
  - baptisms, funerals, and weddings 1980 - 1989 (Box 10)
  - baptisms, funerals, and weddings 1990 - 2010 (Box 10)
  - baptisms, funerals, and weddings undated (Box 10)
- SERIES IV: Writings
  - "Conscience in the Thought of Dietrich Bonhoeffer" 1950 (Box 11)
  - "Doctrine of Vocation and the Problem of Work in Modern Society" 1962 (Box 11)
  - "Jonathan Edwards" 1960 (Box 11)
  - "Rethinking Childhood" 2004 (Box 11)
  - "Vanishing Absolutes" 1965 (Box 11)
  - various monographs and anthologies undated (Box 11)
  - sermons, speeches, and addresses 1950 - 1954 (Box 12)
  - sermons, speeches, and addresses 1955 - 1956 (Box 12)
  - sermons, speeches, and addresses 1957 (Box 12)
  - sermons, speeches, and addresses 1958 (Box 12)
  - sermons, speeches, and addresses 1959 (Box 13)
  - sermons, speeches, and addresses 1960 - 1961 (Box 13)
  - sermons, speeches, and addresses 1962 - 1964 (Box 13)
  - sermons, speeches, and addresses 1965 - 1966 (Box 14)
  - sermons, speeches, and addresses 1967 - 1968 (Box 15)
  - sermons, speeches, and addresses 1969 (Box 15)
  - sermons, speeches, and addresses 1970 - 1972 (Box 15)
  - sermons, speeches, and addresses 1973 (Box 15)
  - sermons, speeches, and addresses 1974 (Box 15)
  - sermons, speeches, and addresses 1975 (Box 16)
  - sermons, speeches, and addresses 1976 (Box 16)
  - sermons, speeches, and addresses 1978 (Box 16)
  - sermons, speeches, and addresses 1979 (Box 16)
  - sermons, speeches, and addresses 1980 - 1982 (Box 16)
  - sermons, speeches, and addresses 1983 - 1984 (Box 16)
  - sermons, speeches, and addresses 1985 - 1989 (Box 16)
  - sermons, speeches, and addresses 1990 - 2010 (Box 16)
  - sermons, speeches, and addresses undated (Box 16)
  - Trocme: bibliography undated (Box 17)
  - Trocme: correspondence (Annick Flaud) 2003 - 2005 (Box 17)
  - Trocme: correspondence (family) undated (Box 17)
  - Trocme: correspondence (family) 1993 - 2002 (Box 17)
  - Trocme: correspondence (family) restricted (Box 17)
  - Trocme: correspondence (miscellaneous) undated (Box 17)
  - Trocme: correspondence (publishers) 2005 (Box 17)
  - Trocme: photographs 1880 - 2008 (Box 17)
  - Trocme: publication 2012 - 2014 (Box 17)
  - Trocme: interviews undated (Box 18)
  - Trocme: research notes undated (Box 18)
  - Trocme: research notes undated (Box 18)
  - Trocme: research trip 2001 (Box 18)
  - Trocme: research trip 2002 (Box 18)
  - Trocme: introduction - chapter 3 undated (Box 19)
  - Trocme: chapter 4 - chapter 6 undated (Box 19)
  - Trocme: chapter 7 - chapter 9 undated (Box 19)
  - Trocme: chapter 10 - chapter 14 undated (Box 19)
  - Trocme: chapter 15 - chapter 18 undated (Box 19)
  - Trocme: draft undated (Box 20)
- SERIES V: Audiovisual Materials
  - Trocme, Music, Family 1960 - 2008 (Box 21)
  - Northfield Mount Hermon 1980 - 1995 (Box 22)
  - Smith College 1960 - 2000 (Box 23)